Preliminary Inventory of the Edmund Jan Osmańczyk Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Edmund Jan Osmańczyk papers
1937-1989
2013C2
Hoover Institution Archives
84 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (34 linear feet)
Correspondence, writings, and printed matter, relating to political conditions in Poland, Polish foreign relations, and international relations in general.
Osmańczyk, Edmund Jan
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2012.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Edmund Osmańczyk (1913-1989) was a Polish journalist, writer, politician, and Silesian activist. He served as parliamentary deputy from 1952 to 1961 and 1969 to 1985. His life was rather atypical for his generation of Polish intellectuals; unlike most others, who were either killed or had to leave the country, he survived the war and forty-five years of communism, and died in free Poland.
Born on the extreme western periphery of ethnic Poland, in mostly German Silesia, Osmańczyk studied in Warsaw and in Berlin. His journalistic career began in the 1930s as a correspondent covering the League of Nations in Geneva. Later he directed the press of the Union of Poles in Germany, an organization concerned with the welfare of over a million ethnic Poles and Polish immigrants living in pre-World War II Germany. Threatened with arrest by the Gestapo, Osmańczyk moved to Warsaw and got a job with the Polish State Radio. When the Nazis invaded Poland in September 1939, he joined the underground, working for its clandestine radio in Warsaw. He lived through the Warsaw Uprising, and, in early 1945, he joined the Polish troops fighting alongside the Red Army. He was a war correspondent during the battle for Berlin, the Potsdam Conference, and the Nuremberg trials of Nazi war criminals.
An enthusiastic and vocal supporter of Poland's rights to its formerly German "Recovered Territories," and uncritical of Polish Communists and their Soviet sponsors, Osmańczyk worked for the Polish state radio and the press agency without having to join the Communist Party. His radio and press assignments took him to various countries in Europe, the United States, and Latin America. Along with a small group of Catholic and unaffiliated intellectuals, Osmańczyk served in the parliament of Polish People's Republic for close to thirty years, through 1985, helping provide a semblance of democratic diversity to this largely symbolic institution. In the waning years of communist Poland, during the social and political ascendancy of the Solidarity trade union movement of the 1980s, Edmund Osmańczyk joined the democratic opposition. He was one of the Solidarity representatives in the roundtable discussions with the Communists that paved the way for a peaceful transition from authoritarian communism to a parliamentary democracy in Poland. In the first semifree parliamentary elections in the Soviet Bloc, on June 4 1989, Osmańczyk was elected senator. He was able to enjoy his democratic mandate, political popularity, and respect only briefly, dying of a heart attack four months later.
Osmańczyk authored some two dozen books and hundreds of articles. His most substantial work was the four-volume Encyclopedia of the United Nations and International Agreements, with an introduction by Secretary General Javier Perez de Cuellar, published in several editions in Polish, English, and Spanish. Osmańczyk, an old acquaintance of Witold Sworakowski, director of the Hoover Institution Library and Archives was probably the first scholar from communist Poland and the Soviet Bloc to conduct research at the Hoover Library and Archives. After his October 1956 visit to Stanford, Osmanczyk published a detailed report on some of the Polish holdings of the Hoover Library and Archives; it remains a useful tool for researchers.
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, writings, and printed matter, relating to political conditions in Poland, Polish foreign relations, and international relations in general.
Journalism--Poland.; Journalists.; Poland--Foreign relations--1945-1989.; Poland--Politics and government--1945-1980.; Poland--Politics and government--1980-1989.; World politics--1945-1989.
- Box 1 - Box 46
  - "Inni i my. Wymowa dokumentów,” Dziennik Polski, 1946 November 20 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - "Matka Boska Radosna," Tygodnik Powszechny, 1945 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    Also Includes
    "Na ziemiach Odzyskanych (I), Mówimy prawdę”, Dziennik Polski, 21.7.1945, nr. 164 (Rewers strony 3); E. J. Osmańczyk, "Na ziemiach Odzyskanych (IV)”, Wrocławskie Wrota, Dziennik Polski, 12.8.1945, nr. 186, s. 3; E. J. Osmańczyk, "Na ziemiach Odzyskanych (III), Bertram nie ustąpił”, Dziennik Polski, nr. 168, 25.7,1945; "Na ziemiach Odzyskanych (VI), Szczecin jest polski”, Dziennik Polski, nr 189, 15.8.1945
  - "Żywot i śmierć Berlina," Sprawozdanie korespondenta wojennego, 1945 May 25 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - "Raport z niemieckiego rynku pracy," Dziennik Zachodni, 1948 May 5 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - "Krótkie spięcie (nad tytuł)," "Z życia kleru," Dziennik Polski, 1947 August 16 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - "Rozmowy z Niemcami: Lipsk-liczby, ludzie, liderzy…," Dziennik Zachodni, 1947 February 27 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - "Pasjonująca literatura," Dziennik Literacki Polski, 1948 June 6-12 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - "Starzy znajomi i co ich łączy," Dziennik Polski, 1948 July 7 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - "Reforma walutowa w Niemczech," Dziennik Polski, 1948 June 4 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - "Reporter klasyczny," Dziennik Polski-Literacki, 1948 April 25 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - "Sprawa się wyjaśnia," Dziennik Polski, 1948 September 25 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - "Milczący Mr. Brüning" (Od własnego korespondenta API dla Dziennika Polskiego), Dziennik Polski, 1948 September 6 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - "Trzy lata Poczdamu(I), Ideały Zwycięzców,", undated (Box-folder 1: 13)
    E. J. Osmańczyk, "Trzy lata Poczdamu (II), Ciężar okupacji"; "Trzy lata Poczdamu (III)"; "Nerwówka"
  - "Rozmowy z Niemcami (3), Na południe od Berlina," Dziennik Polski, 1948 February 23 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - "Liczby i fakty," Dziennik Polski, 1948 February 27 (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - "Sprawa wschodnich uciekinierów," Dziennik Polski, 1948 January 28 (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - "Odbudowa ciężkiego przemysłu niemieckiego," Dziennik Polski, 1948 March 14 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - "Nowiny za serbski lud," Dziennik Polski, 1948 April 13 (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - "Tu i tam denazyfikacja skończona," Dziennik Polski, 1948 March 9 (Box-folder 1: 19)
  - "Frankfurcki gabinet," Dziennik Polski, 1948 January 15 (Box-folder 1: 20)
  - "Rozmowy z Niemcami, W stolicy Saksonii - w radzieckiej strefie okupacyjnej," Dziennik Polski, 1948 (Box-folder 1: 21)
  - "Notatka (x2) w sprawie Łużyc, współpraca koresp. woj.," Praga, 1945 July 5 (Box-folder 1: 22)
  - "Przez Kłodzko do Pragi," Dziennik Polski (kwiecień, Kłodzko), undated (Box-folder 1: 23)
  - Mieciu Nowak z Niechomu, "Łużyccy Serbowie," Czytelnik, undated (Box-folder 1: 24)
  - "Sprawy Polaków," Słowo Polskie, Wydawnictwo Awir, 1946 March (Box-folder 1: 25)
  - J. A. Szczepański, "Polacy i Niemcy," Dziennik Polski, undated (Box-folder 1: 26)
  - "Polacy nad Odrą,", undated (Box-folder 1: 27)
  - "Na roboty do Prus,", undated (Box-folder 1: 28)
  - "Reforma rolna nad Odrą," (rękopis), 1945 March 27 (Box-folder 1: 29)
  - "Kraj Krzywdy," (maszynopis rozdział do Spraw Polaków), 1945 March (Box-folder 1: 30)
  - "Gdański finał a gdańskie dzieci," (maszynopis ad. Książka), undated (Box-folder 1: 31)
  - "Niebezpieczne złudzenia," (maszynopis), undated (Box-folder 1: 32)
  - "Idea czy terytorium," (maszynopis), undated (Box-folder 1: 33)
  - "Bei den Preussen," Odra, (maszynopis), undated (Box-folder 1: 34)
  - "Bei den Preussen," Odra, (maszynopis), undated (Box-folder 1: 35)
  - "Korzenie hitleryzmu," (artykuł 5), (maszynopis), undated (Box-folder 1: 36)
  - "Polacy nad Odrą," (maszynopis), artykuł siódmy, undated (Box-folder 1: 37)
  - "Na pobojowisku," (maszynopis), undated (Box-folder 1: 38)
  - "Skazani i przeklęci," Przekrój, (3 x maszynopis), undated (Box-folder 1: 39)
  - "Polityka realna Polaków," (2 x maszynopis), undated (Box-folder 1: 40)
  - "Znam tylko jeden Śląsk," (książka i do Odry), (maszynopis), undated (Box-folder 1: 41)
  - "Na zachodzie jest ziemia," (dla Zaremby Łódź, II Odra, Tygodnik Powszechny, archiwum), (maszynopis), undated (Box-folder 1: 42)
  - "Cierpliwość roztropna," Paryż, sierpień 1946, Czytelnik, (maszynopis), 1946 August (Box-folder 1: 43)
  - "Norymberga w Paryżu," Czytelnik, (maszynopis), 1946 August (Box-folder 1: 44)
  - "Spotkania w Genewie," Dziennik Polski, Genewa, (maszynopis), 1946 August (Box-folder 1: 45)
  - "Gisevius i Pechem," Odra, (maszynopis), undated (Box-folder 1: 46)
  - "W Szleswigu walka trwa. Flensburg w czerwcu," (maszynopis), undated (Box-folder 1: 47)
  - "W Paryżu, w Berlinie i w Sztutgarcie," Tygodnik Powszechny, (maszynopis), undated (Box-folder 1: 48)
  - "Berlin i Rzesza," Odra, Berlin, (maszynopis), 1947 April (Box-folder 1: 49)
  - "Saara powraca do Francji," Berlin, API, Czytelnik, (maszynopis), 1947 January (Box-folder 1: 50)
  - "Der Friede von Warsachau?," API, Czytelnik, (maszynopis), undated (Box-folder 1: 51)
  - "Uzasadniona nieufność," Przekrój, (maszynopis), undated (Box-folder 1: 52)
  - "A B C o Niemczech," Przekrój, (maszynopis), undated (Box-folder 1: 53)
  - "27 portretów," Przekrój, (maszynopis), undated (Box-folder 1: 54)
  - "Dwa głosy niemieckie," Odra, (maszynopis), undated (Box-folder 1: 55)
  - "Z lotu ptaka," Przekrój, (2 x maszynopis), undated (Box-folder 1: 56)
  - "Wstąpiła w nas nadzieja," (maszynopis), undated (Box-folder 1: 57)
  - "Kontakty niemieckie z zagranicą," API, Czytelnik, (maszynopis), undated (Box-folder 1: 58)
  - "Pieniądz Trzeciej Rzeszy," (2 x maszynopis), undated (Box-folder 1: 59)
  - "Konferencja szesnastu," Przekrój, Paryż, (2 x maszynopis), 1947 July (Box-folder 1: 60)
  - "Polacy na Westfalii i Nadrenii," (maszynopis), undated (Box-folder 1: 61)
  - "Nowe Książki: Dzieje Głupoty w Polsce," Przekrój, (maszynopis), undated (Box-folder 1: 62)
  - "Przemówienie Bidault,", 1947 December 7 (Box-folder 1: 63)
  - Projekt tygodnika polskiego na Niemcy, undated (Box-folder 1: 64)
  - "Polska w Europie i świecie," (rękopis), undated (Box-folder 1: 65)
  - "Rosjanie i Polacy," Przekrój, (rękopis), undated (Box-folder 1: 66)
  - "Przyszłość Niemiec," Odczyt, (rękopis), undated (Box-folder 1: 67)
  - "Troska i śmierć," Przekrój, (rękopis), undated (Box-folder 1: 68)
  - Pismo do redaktora naczelnego Wiadomości, Berlin, (maszynopis), 1946 October 22 (Box-folder 1: 69)
  - "47 dzień blokady Berlina," Przekrój, (wycinek), 1948 August (Box-folder 1: 70)
  - Spis przedstawicielstw, U.S. Press Center, Berlin, dokument, 1950 May 28 (Box-folder 1: 71)
  - "Polacy w Niemczech," Notatka dotycząca mniejszości Polaków w Niemczech, (maszynopis), undated (Box-folder 1: 72)
  - Ocena pracy E. Osmańczyka, "Podstawy polityki polskiej po II wojnie światowej," (maszynopis), undated (Box-folder 1: 73)
  - Stanisław Zenkteler, Fragmenty z poematu "Edmund,", 1959 December 29 (Box-folder 1: 74)
    Fragment z I części: Berlin, 1939,
  - “An Folk und Werhmacht,” (Odezwa), 1944 December 8 (Box-folder 1: 75)
  - “Na pobojowisku,” Tygodnik Odrodzenie, Kraków, (artykuł), 1945 April 15 (Box-folder 1: 76)
  - "Reinich Westfaelische Zeitung," National Zeitung, 1944 September 5 (Box-folder 1: 77)
  - Nowy Kurier Warszawski, Wydanie Specjalne, 1944 August 15 (Box-folder 1: 78)
  - Ulotka: "Slezane, Pratele Szelska," Slezsky Kulturni Ustav, undated (Box-folder 1: 79)
  - Nowy Kurier Warszawski, nr. 7, 1945 January 9 (Box-folder 1: 80)
  - "Mitteilungen fur das Officierkorps, Oberkommando der Wehrmacht," Sondernummer, undated (Box-folder 1: 81)
  - "Um die Zunkunft der Deutschen," Der Politische Soldat, 1945 January (Box-folder 1: 82)
  - "Befehl 1, Antifaschistische Freiheitsbewegung Zwigstelle Bischodswalde, Bischofswalde," (maszynopis, Odpis 1), 1945 June 15 (Box-folder 1: 83)
  - Przepustka do metra, (Ausweis), 1945 January 25 (Box-folder 1: 84)
  - "DNB vertrauliches Rohmaterial," nr. 43, 12.02.1944, (maszynopis) ditto DNB vertrauliches Rohmaterial, nr. 96, 1944 April 5 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - "Ogłoszenia dla Zgorzelca i okolic," (po niemiecku), (artykuł), 1945 June 30 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - “Hard to realize Poland was on winner,” (Wycinek prasowy) (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - "Odrodzenie Nacjonalizmu niemieckiego," Tygodnik Polski, Londyn, nr. 46, (artykuł), 1947 November 29 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - "Krótkie notatki z Californii, Gwiazda Polarna," Stevens Point, WIS., (wycinek prasowy), 1947 November 8 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Menu, undated (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Travel order PRS/BPC/11 – lot do strefy wojskowej Berlina, (Headqurters Rhein Main af Base, Apo 57, US Army), 1948 December 15 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Travel order PRS/BPC/11 dla M. Podkowiński, E. Osmańczyk, Berlin, 1948 April 28 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Dokument podróży (radziecki) dla E. J. Osmańczyk, 1948 April 28 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - ditto Dokument podróży (radziecki) dla E. J. Osmańczyk, 1948 May 1 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Akredytacja E. J. Osmańczyka, (Czytelnik), 1948 December 9 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - Zawiadomienie o przyznaniu nagrody za pracę "Śląsk w Polsce Ludowej," Instytut Historii PAN, 1954 December 17 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - Zaświadczenie polskiej misji wojskowej dla władz wojskowych, Berlin, 1950 December 6 (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - List do U.S. Press-Center, Berlin, 1946 April 7 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - red. A. Bartosz, "Z naszej niwy," Przedruki i komentarze o sprawach polskich, (wycinek prasowy), 1947 November 1 (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - Upoważnienie wejścia do bazy rybackiej w Świnoujściu, Dyrekcja budowy bazy rybackiej, Świnoujście, 1951 June 11 (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - "Berliner Rundfunk," Berlin, 1951 September 29 (Box-folder 2: 17)
  - Niemiecka Akademia Nauk, Berlin, (dot. sprawy łużyckiej, Jan Skala, maszynopis, list), 1970 February 19 (Box-folder 2: 18)
  - J. I. Kraszewskiego, "Swoboda Słowa," plus list przewodni, Kraków, (maszynopis), 1961 March 23 (Box-folder 2: 19)
  - Niemiecki program telewizyjny (ad. Wybór Papieża Jana Pawła II), Quick, nr. 43, 1978 October 22 (Box-folder 2: 20)
  - J. Koller, "... nie literackie," Dziennik Poznański, nr. 107, 1938 May 11 (Box-folder 2: 21)
  - Polish Arts and Culture Foundation, 3 numery z 1987, 1987 April (Box-folder 2: 22)
  - Reklama znaczków ONZ, 4 egzemplarze, undated (Box-folder 2: 23)
  - Polski Komitet Pokoju, List w sprawie zgromadzenia budowniczych pokoju w Warszawie, podpisany J. Cyrankiewicz, plus projekt obrad, 1977 April 28 (Box-folder 2: 24)
  - Zaświadczenie Komisji Wyborczej o wyborze E. J. Osmańczyka na posła PRL, Tekst ślubowania, 1976 March 21 (Box-folder 2: 25)
  - Pismo w sprawie powołania Krajowego Obywatelskiego Komitetu Obchodów Święta Odrodzenia Polski, podpisano H. Jabłoński, Przewodniczący Ogólnopolskiego Komitetu Frontu Narodowego, 1977 July 1 (Box-folder 2: 26)
  - Pismo/list z okazji nadania tytułu D. H. E. J. Osmańczykowi Uniwersytetu Śląskiego w Katowicach, podpisano prof. dr hab. S. Kaliski, 1975 October 2 (Box-folder 2: 27)
  - Powinszowania z okazji nadania D. H., podpisano gen. brygady Jerzy Ziętek, członek Rady Państwa, 1975 October 27 (Box-folder 2: 28)
  - Powiadomienie o przyznaniu Krzyża Komandorskiego za zasługi w dziedzinie publicystyki, brak podpisu, undated (Box-folder 2: 29)
  - Życzenia Noworoczne, podpisane E. Gierek, 1976 (Box-folder 2: 30)
  - Życzenia Noworoczne, podpisane E. Gierek, 1975 (Box-folder 2: 31)
  - Zawiadomienie o przyznaniu nagrody za działalność w zakresie publicystyki radiowej, podpisane Maciej Szczepański, 1975 May 14 (Box-folder 2: 32)
  - Notatka dla Pierwszego Sekretarza KC PZPR nt. stosunków z NRF, 1974 April 21 (Box-folder 2: 33)
  - Notatka w sprawie układu NRF-NRD-Polska, Notatka dla Towarzysza Gierka, undated (Box-folder 2: 34)
  - Zawiadomienie o rozwiązaniu Rady Programowej ds. Radia i TV, podpisane Włodzimierz Sokorski, 1970 March 3 (Box-folder 2: 35)
  - Zawiadomienie o nowym statucie organizacyjnym Komitetu ds. radia i TV i powołaniu w skład członków Rady Programowej Radia i TV, podpisano Włodzimierz Sokorski, 1970 March 3 (Box-folder 2: 36)
  - Zawiadomienie o uroczystym posiedzeniu Sejmu z okazji XXX PRL, podpisano Marszałek Sejmu, 1974 July 21 (Box-folder 2: 37)
  - Zaproszenie na Jubileusz (5-lecie) miesięcznika Opole, podpisano Jan Goczoł, Opole, 1975 May 15 (Box-folder 2: 38)
  - Tekst ślubowania poselskiego do Sejmu PRL, Warszawa, 1969 (Box-folder 2: 39)
  - Zawiadomienie o wyborze do Sejmu z listy Frontu Jedności Narodu, Warszawa, 1969 June 2 (Box-folder 2: 40)
  - Notatka/odpowiedź (tajna) do Ministra Spraw Wewnętrznych, IV.026/71 dotycząca kontroli osób odpowiedzialnych za emigrację do NRF, 1971 May 8 (Box-folder 2: 41)
  - Aneks w sprawie Układu z PRL (NRF), 1970 December 8 (Box-folder 2: 42)
  - Zawiadomienie nt. interpelacji E. J. Osmańczyka dotyczącej wrogiej propagandy wokół kwestii wyjazdów do NRF w ramach łączenia rodzi, podpisane Marszałek Sejmu, 1971 April 23 (Box-folder 2: 43)
  - Interpelacja poselska, w sprawie wrogiej propagandy dot. wyjazdów do Niemiec, 1971 February 18 (Box-folder 2: 44)
  - Interpelacja poselska na ręce Premiera Piotra Jaroszewicza (plus fragmenty tekstu przemówienia E. Gierka na VIII Plenum KC PZPR, 1971 February 17 (Box-folder 2: 45)
  - Pismo przewodnie Marszałka Sejmu do E. J. Osmańczyka w odpowiedzi na interpelacje w sprawie wyjazdów do NRF, odpis pisma Wiceprezesa RM Wincentego Kraśko do Marszałka Sejmu w sprawie interpelacji E. J. Osmańczyka, podpisano Wiceprezes RM W. Kraśko, 1971 March 18 (Box-folder 2: 46)
  - List przewodni do czasopisma Poglądy (Katowice "Polski Problem"), nr. 1, tire Warszawa (maszynopis, kopia dla J. Szydlaka), undated (Box-folder 2: 47)
  - Notatka dla Towarzysza Gierka nt. Układu NRF-NRD-Polska, Warszawa, 1970 November 10 (Box-folder 2: 48)
  - Projekt postulatów wspólnej Komisji Spraw Wewnętrznych i Spraw Zagranicznych, maszynopis, 1971 June (Box-folder 2: 49)
  - List do E. Gierka, dotyczący tez na kolejny Zjazd jesienny 1971, (maszynopis i rękopis), 1971 November 6 (Box-folder 2: 50)
  - List przewodni w sprawie wypowiedzi przed VI zjazdem Partii, Warszawa, podpisano E. Gierek, 1971 October (Box-folder 2: 51)
  - Notatka dla I Sekretarza KCPZPR (brudnopis), 1972 January 6 (Box-folder 2: 52)
  - Pismo Kierownika Wydziału Zagranicznego KC PZPR, R. Frelka, w sprawie opinii stosunków dwustronnych PRL-NRF na podstawie układu z grudnia 1970, 1972 March 13 (Box-folder 2: 53)
  - Gratulacje do Ministra Nauki Szkolnictwa Wyższego i Techniki z tytułu przyznania D.H., podpisano Minister S. Kaliski, 1975 October 2 (Box-folder 2: 54)
  - Zaproszenie na otwarcie VII Zjazdu PZPR, 1975 December 8 (Box-folder 2: 55)
  - Gratulacje z tytułu nadania D.H. Uniwersytetu Śląskiego, 1975 October 2 (Box-folder 2: 56)
  - Prośba o przedstawienie /sugestie co do propozycji w sprawach, które powinny być przedmiotem VII zjazdu PZPR, podpisano Gierek, 1975 July 10 (Box-folder 2: 57)
  - Podziękowanie Instytutu Śląskiego za uczestnictwo w rozwój placówki, 1977 May 27 (Box-folder 2: 58)
  - Notatka w sprawie 50-lecia Związku Polaków w Niemczech, czerwiec 1971, rękopis, 1971 June (Box-folder 2: 59)
  - List do J. Szydlaka (missing item), 1972 January 16 (Box-folder 2: 60)
  - "Dodatek nadzwyczajny," Nowy Kurier Warszawski, notatka odręczna E. J. Osmańczyka: wydane w Warszawie w lecie 1943 r., 2 egzemplarz znaleziony w Warszawie w Gestapo, niedziela kwiecień 1945 (art. prasowy), 1945 April (Box-folder 2: 61)
  - "Golańskie dzieci," (rękopis), undated (Box-folder 2: 62)
  - "Gdański finał,", 1945 April (Box-folder 2: 63)
  - "W Gdyni i Gdańsku," maszynopis, korespondencja, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 64)
  - "Synowie Krzywoustego," korespondencja, maszynopis, napisane w Berlinie, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 65)
  - Statut oficerów polityczno-wychowawczych, z tyłu adnotacja odręczna, undated (Box-folder 2: 66)
  - List z Berlina, "Żołnierzom Pierwszej Armii walczącym w Berlinie i nad Łabą," wiersz, maszynopis, Warszawa, 1945 April 30 (Box-folder 2: 67)
    Also includes
    "W Opolu," z książki "Wolność jest słoneczna," 1937 r., wiersz, maszynopis, "To do Polski woła Śląsk Opolski," wiersz, maszynopis,
  - Aneks w sprawie strat i pomocy dla zakładu Księży Marianów na Bielanach, wysłany do USA, 1946 November (Box-folder 2: 68)
  - Program uroczystości 1 maja 1932 roku na Bielanach, 1932 May 1 (Box-folder 2: 69)
  - Serwis informacyjny Agencji Prasowo-Informacyjnej, Londyn, 14.01.1944, ocenzurowano, 1949 (?), maszynopis, 1944 January 14 (Box-folder 2: 70)
  - Komunikat 589, Deklaracja Rady Jedności Narodowej i Krajowej Rady Ministrów, 1945 February 13 (Box-folder 2: 71)
  - Komunikat 590 PAT (Polska Agencja Telegraficzna) z Nowego Jorku, 1945 February 14 (Box-folder 2: 72)
  - "Majowe refleksje z 1945 roku," rękopis, artykuł, 1975 May 3 (Box-folder 2: 73)
  - "Pierwszy maja 1945 w Berlinie," Poglądy, wspomnienie, maszynopis, 1945 May 1 (Box-folder 2: 74)
  - "Dwie ziemie święte," Przegląd kulturalny, kwiecień 1960 rok, maszynopis, 1960 April (Box-folder 2: 75)
  - Wycinek prasowy z gazety (?), "Z naszej niwy,", 1944 October 21 (Box-folder 2: 76)
  - Komunikat Polish Press Agency, Nowy Jork, 1945 February 2 (Box-folder 2: 77)
  - Komentarz PAT (Polish Telegraph Agency), 1944 October (Box-folder 2: 78)
  - Uchwała w sprawie Komisja Okręgowej PZPR, Centralna Komisja Kontroli Partyjnej, dotyczy Zbigniewa Mitznera, 1957 November 25 (Box-folder 2: 79)
  - "Czy będzie pokój czy wojna?," Poradnik Rolnika, maszynopis, undated (Box-folder 2: 80)
  - List prywatny do E. J. Osmańczyka, podpisano Urszula Jaszczyk, 1957 April 26 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - "Pozdrowienia dla Opola," Trybuna Opolska, maszynopis, 1957 June 10 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - Maszynopis nt. rozpoczętego procesu norymberskiego, undated (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - Maszynopis nt. rozpoczętego procesu norymberskiego, undated (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Maszynopis nt. rozpoczętego procesu norymberskiego, undated (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - Maszynopis nt. rozpoczętego procesu norymberskiego, undated (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - "Matka Boska Radosna," Tygodnik Powszechny, nr. 17, 1945, maszynopis (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - Maszynopis "Dopiski do historii,", undated (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - L. Bartelski, "Trzy nagrody," Wieś, nr. 3, wycinek, undated (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - Wycinki prasowe trzech artykułów: "Jasno i otwarcie o sprawie niemieckiej," Odrodzenie, ad. Sprawy Polaków, undated (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - "Poeta Ojczyzny z serc," Jutro Polski, nr. 12, 1946 r. (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - "Strona rozmaitości," Przekrój, wycinek prasowy, undated (Box-folder 3: 12)
  - Maszynopis dla Miesięcznika Literackiego, 1978 June (Box-folder 3: 13)
  - 'Kraj krzywdy," Tygodnik Odrodzenie, 1945 March 18 (Box-folder 3: 14)
  - "Na pobojowisku," Tygodnik Odrodzenie, 1945 April 15 (Box-folder 3: 15)
  - Maszynopis do Pełnomocnika Tymczasowego Rządu RP gen. Zawadzkiego, Katowice, 1945 February 12 (Box-folder 3: 16)